Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Dean of Students records, 1923-1998 MVC0041.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Dean of Students records
1923-1998
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0041.RG
2.75 Linear Feet
This collection contains student handbooks from Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1923 to 1998.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains student handbooks from Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1923 to 1998.
Biographical / Historical
In general, the Dean of Students oversees a wide range of student services including: administrative services, student health and wellness, academic support, career development, and leadership programs.
The Mount Vernon Seminary began in 1875 as a private high school and junior college for women, founded by Elizabeth J. Somers. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999.
The first school of higher education available to women in Washington, D.C., Mount Vernon Seminary and College had five different locations throughout its history:
1875-1880: Elizabeth Somers began tutoring the young daughters of prominent Washington men in her home at 204 F Street, NW in Washington, DC.
1880-1917: The school moved to 1100 M Street, NW where it expanded rapidly to include three additional houses, a courtyard, tennis court, and basketball court.
1917-1942: Having outgrown its M Street location, the school moved to a 15.5-acre campus on Nebraska Avenue, NW. The buildings and layout of the campus were designed by a New York architect, Wesley S. Bessell. and the campus was formally dedicated on November 5, 1917 -- Mrs. Somers' 80th birthday. In 1942, the United States Navy took over the Nebraska Avenue campus to use its facilities for the war effort.
1943-1946: The school resumed courses in February 1943 at the top floor of a Garfinckel's department store building in the Spring Valley neighborhood of Washington, D.C.
1946-1999: Between 1944 and 1946, the school built a new 21-acre campus located on Foxhall Road in Washington, D.C. using money granted to the college by the United States Navy in compensation for the military takeover of its property.
The last Seminary class graduated in 1969, and the school was then officially renamed to Mount Vernon Junior College. In 1976, Mount Vernon College became an accredited four year college. In 1997, the Board of Trustees decided that the College would close as an independent institution. As of June 30, 1999, Mount Vernon became affiliated with The George Washington University.
Arrangement
Currently organized into one series: Student handbooks.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection is from Mount Vernon College, which The George Washington University acquired in 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Students; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
- Student handbooks, 1923-1998; Series 1; 2.75 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Seminary School handbooks, Junior College handbooks, and Mount Vernon College handbooks.
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series include student handbooks from Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1923 to 1998.
  The student handbooks from Mount Vernon Seminary, Junior College, and College contain a wide range of information including but not limited to: rules and regulations (dress code, acadmic honor code, code of conduct, daily schedules, visiting hours, judicial process, etc.), lists of clubs and activities, Mount Vernon traditions, important dates and phone number, and names of members of various student organizations.
  Some handbooks also include messages of welcome from the school's president, photographs of current students, the alma mater, and drawings of the campus.
  - Seminary School handbooks, 1923-1965; Series 1 Subseries 1
    Arranged chronologically.
    The materials of this subseries include student handbooks from Mount Vernon Seminary. They range in date from 1923 to 1965.
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1923-1924; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder data_value_missing_eace4c18afbfecf2d960eefc74443e07)
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1924-1925; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - MVS Student's Hanbook, 1925-1931; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1926-1927; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1927-1928; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1928-1929; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1929-1930; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1930-1931; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1931-1932; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - MVS Student's Handbook, 1932-1933; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, mid 1930s; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1939-1940; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, circa 1943-1944; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1948-1949; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1949-1950; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1951-1953; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1951-1952; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1953-1954; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1954-1955; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1955-1956; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1956-1957; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1957-1958; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1958-1959; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1959-1960; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1960-1961; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Preparatory School Handbook, 1962-1965; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Summary of Rules and Regulations, MVS, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Junior College handbooks, 1934-1970; Series 1 Subseries 2
    The materials of this subseries include student handbooks from Mount Vernon Junior College. They range in date from 1934-1970.
    - Junior College Handbook, 1934-1935; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Junior College Handbook, mid 1930s; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Junior College Handbook, 1945-1946; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Junior College Handbook, 1949-1950; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Junior College Handbook, 1950-1951; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Junior College Handbook, 1953-1954; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Junior College Handbook, 1954-1955; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mount Vernon Handbook, 1955-1956; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Mount Vernon Handbook, 1956-1957; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Mount Vernon Handbook, 1957-1958; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Mount Vernon Handbook, 1958-1959; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Mount Vernon Handbook, 1959-1960; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Mount Vernon Handbook, 1961-1963; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Mount Vernon Handbook, 1963-1964; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Mount Vernon Handbook, 1964-1965; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Mount Vernon Junior College Student Handbook, 1967-1970; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mount Vernon College handbooks, 1970-1998; Series 1 Subseries 3
    The materials of this subseries include student handbooks from Mount Vernon College. They range in date from 1970-1998.
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1970-1971; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1971-1972; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1972-1973; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1973-1974; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1974-1975; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook and LRC Student Handbook, 1976-1977; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1977-1978; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Mount Vernon College Academic Handbook, 1978-1979; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1978-1979; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1979-1989; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Mount Vernon College Academic Handbook, 1979-1980; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1980-1981; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Mount Vernon College Academic Handbook, 1980-1981; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Student/Academic Handbook, 1981-1982; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Student/Academic Handbook, 1982-1983; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Student/Academic Handbook, 1983-1984; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Student/Academic Handbook, 1984-1985; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Student/Academic Handbook, 1985-1986; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Student/Academic Handbook, 1986-1987; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Student/Academic Handbook, 1987-1988; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Mount Vernon College Student and Academic Handbook, 1988-1989; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Mount Vernon College Student/Academic Handbook, 1989-1990; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Resource Handbook, 1990-1991; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Student Resource Handbook, 1991-1992; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Student Resource Handbook, 1992-1993; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Student Handbook, 1993-1994; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1994-1995; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1995-1996; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1996-1997; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Mount Vernon College Student Handbook, 1997-1998; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 2, Folder 4)